Thomas Higgins, Jr. Papers
Thomas Higgins, Jr. Papers
1957-1971
Higgins, Tom, 1922-2000.
1 linear ft.
Original cartoons, sketches, proofs, clippings and correspondence.
4205071
Biographical History
Thomas J. Higgins, Jr. (1922-2000) was an American cartoonist. Over the course of his long career, his cartoons appeared in many major magazines and trade journals.
Higgins was born in Far Rockaway, New York. During World War II, while stationed in Japan shortly after the dropping of the atomic bomb, his lungs were so badly damaged that Higgins required a two year convalescence in a military hospital. Upon his return to New York after the War, he enrolled in the Cartoonists and Illustrators School and was soon working as a free lance cartoonist.
Higgins' specialty was producing cartoons for niche publications and trade journals, but he also had a number of cartoons published in major magazines like the Saturday Evening Post, Argosy, Theatre Arts, Extension and Parade. Higgins continued to work as a professional cartoonist until his death in San Diego, California.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Thomas Higgins, Jr. Papers contains correspondence, original artwork, and published material. Much of the published material appeared in various trade or professional publications such as Illinois Master Plumber (plumbers), Hotel and Club Voice (for hotel, bartender and restaurant workers), and Safe Driving News, a publication of Kennametal (manufacturer of studded tires).
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Higgins, Tom, 1922-2000.; Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Beatles -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Magazine illustration.; Cartoons (humorous images); Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Portraits.; Sketches.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Thomas Higgins, Jr., 1966-1968, 1971.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, A-Z, 1965-1967; 1971; includes some original art (Box 1)
- Original artwork
  - Amebic Amiabilities, 1966-1967; undated; includes two clippings of printed items from Antibiotic News and a small amount of correspondence (Box 1)
  - Cartoons, undated (Box 1)
  - Kennametal, 1968; undated; includes two clippings of printed items from their "Kengrip" newsletter (Box 1)
  - Portraits of the Beatles, 1964; includes newspaper clipping of published version (Box 1)
  - Sketches, undated (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Advertiser-Democrat (Norway and South Paris, Maine), 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - Antibiotic News ("Amebic Amiabilities"), See Original artwork: Amebic Amiabilities.
  - Chicago Purchaser, 1958; undated (Box 1)
  - Concrete Highways, undated (Box 1)
  - Eastern Ski Bulletin, undated (Box 1)
  - Exhaust, 1966; undated (Box 1)
  - "Harriet Hobby and Hubby", undated (Box 1)
  - Hotel and Club Voice, 1953; undated; includes numerous items in Spanish (Box 1)
  - Illinois Master Plumber, 1962; 1963,; 1966 (Box 1)
  - Kennametal, See Original artwork: Kennametal.
  - McNeil Laboratories, 1964-1967; includes correspondence and some original art as well (Oversize 1)
  - Modern Retailer, 1962; undated (Box 1)
  - Music Journal, undated (Box 1)
  - Oxford County Fair, 1961; includes one item of original art (Box 1)
  - Philatelic Leader ("Philatoons"), undated (Box 1)
  - Skate, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous publications, A-Z, 1957-1961 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified publications, 1959; undated (Box 1)